<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth vindicated from the unjust accusations of the Independent Society, in the city of Norvvich. Wherein is proved, 1. That the Church of England is a true church of Christ. 2. That it is a sin to seperate from the true church. 3. That the Independent Society in the city of Norwich is no true church of Christ. 4. Divers reasons and arguments used to perswade men not to seperate from the Church of England and joyne to their Society, shewing the sinfulnesse of so doing. / By S.T. Imprimatur, Ia. Cranford. Aug. 10. 1646.</title>
            <author>Townsend, Sampson.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E351_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201063</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861633</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159848</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94773)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159848)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E351[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth vindicated from the unjust accusations of the Independent Society, in the city of Norvvich. Wherein is proved, 1. That the Church of England is a true church of Christ. 2. That it is a sin to seperate from the true church. 3. That the Independent Society in the city of Norwich is no true church of Christ. 4. Divers reasons and arguments used to perswade men not to seperate from the Church of England and joyne to their Society, shewing the sinfulnesse of so doing. / By S.T. Imprimatur, Ia. Cranford. Aug. 10. 1646.</title>
                  <author>Townsend, Sampson.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Harper, for Gifford Galton, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Kings Armes in the Poultrey.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.T. = Sampson Townsend.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 22th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Separatists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Independent churches --  England --  Norwich --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159848:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TRUTH VINDICATED FROM The unjuſt accuſations of the Independent Society, in the City of NORVVICH.</p>
            <p>Wherein is proved,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the Church of England is a true Church of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That it is a ſin to ſeperate from the true Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That the Independent Society in the City of Norwich is no true Church of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Divers reaſons and arguments uſed to perſwade men not to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the Church of England and joyne to their Society, ſhewing the ſinfulneſſe of ſo doing.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>S.T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Why gaddeſt thou about ſo much to change thy way?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 2.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Theſe be they who ſeperate themſelves,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jude</hi> ver. <hi>19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Where there have not beene care in laying a good foundation at the beginning, and where there is much liberty, what elſe can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted but diviſion?</p>
               <bibl>Mr. <hi>Burroughs Moſes Choice, pag.</hi> 295, 296.</bibl>
            </q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Ia. Cranford.</signed>
                     <date> Aug. 10. 1646.</date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Harper,</hi> for <hi>Gifford Galton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the Kings Armes in the Poultrey. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159848:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159848:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe our dayes under the notion of new light, many are led into darkeneſſe, following thoſe who rank things as they conceit, tyrannizing over the minds of others, obtruding their errors on them as truths, ſo putting their humour in the place of Gods Law: which is (as I conceive) the ground and cauſe of all the Errors, Schiſmes, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and diviſions that are now amongst us; But to prevent miſleading, by following theſe night lights (or lanthorne men, as they are vulgarly called) which will (if followed undoubtedly leade thee out of the right way: I have written this following Treatiſe, and undertaken therein, to deale with thoſe of the City of Norwich, that would not be brought under the power of any man, but would have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience (as they call it) that is to ſay, liberty to live and walke as their fancies move them, not preſcribing to themſelves or others, any ſetled way or rule to walke by, but every one to do what ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth good in their owne eyes,<note place="margin">Iudg. 17.6.</note> and therefore they are truly called Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents. I know it will be objected, I once pleaded for them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be joyned with them, why therefore doe I now write againſt them? I anſwer, before I examined their way, I did judge them to be the true Church of Chriſt, but now I ſee it was my errour ſo to account of them, and I count it no ſhame to confeſſe and revoke it as an errour, for the reaſons mentioned in the following Treatiſe. And it is true, I once deſired of them to underſtand and know their way, with an intent (as I told them) to joyne with them in it, if my judgement could cloſe
<pb facs="tcp:159848:3"/>with them, when I underſtood what was their way, (which they promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to acquaint me with) at which time I did intimate to them, that it was my judgement, to hold communion with other Chriſtians, that were not of their Iudgement and in their way, although I ſhould be a member of their ſociety, which they ſeemed much to diſlike. I told them alſo (I intended) if I were admitted to declare in writing my judgement, what I held concerning their way, which they tooke as great pride in me to attempt, and were much diſpleaſed at me for it. So I waited for the accompliſhment of their promiſe, to acquaint me with their way, but it was never performed, at which I was much troubled, that I might not declare mine owne judgement, and that they would not tell me theirs: I thought light ſhould not be put under a buſhell, but on a Candleſtick, that the way of God ſhould not be concealed, but revealed, that it might be practiſed. Vpon theſe thoughts, I have examined their way, and I finde them (as corrupted, ſo likewiſe) exceedingly divided in their judgements: they doe not ſpeake all the ſame thing, nor walke all in theſame way; All (if I miſtake not) deny the Church of England to be a true Church, but all doe not deny to heare the Miniſters thereof; ſome will heare ſome of them as gifted men, few or none will heare any of them as the Miniſters of Chriſt; all (or moſt) of them thinke it a ſin to heare any Miniſters that ſpeake againſt their way; ſome of them thinke it a ſin to heare any but thoſe that are in their way. They are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in their judgements, in theſe and many other things, (which I forbeare to name) and while they are thus divided, how can their way be cleered? but I ſuppoſe when their judgements be all reconciled, then will the Modell of their way be publiſhed; In the meane time, what comfort can be had to joyne with ſuch a ſociety? To walke in a way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, into how many errors may they run? For a man to enter into a way he is ignorant of, and cannot be informed in, argues him to bee, either weake in the head, or unſound at the heart. Vpon theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I did at a meeting of divers of the Independent ſociety, proteſt againſt their way as unlawfull, and ungodly: ſince which time they
<pb facs="tcp:159848:3"/>have raiſed and ſpread abroad many falſe and ſcandalous reports of me: but my intent (at this time) is not to vindicate my ſelfe, but Gods truth which I preferre ten thouſand times before my owne credit: But if I ſhall perceive they take occaſion from my preſent writing, to vent and ſpread abroad their clamourous reproaches of me, ſo as I ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my ſilence will incurre the ſuſpition of the guilt of ſin or ſenceleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſtupidity under the ſenſurers; I ſhall then (God permitting) cleere my ſelfe, and if in ſo doing, I ſhall make a further diſcovery of them, and make their private miſcarriages publique, I am not to bee blamed, if they neceſsitate mee thereto: In the meane time, I truſt (through the grace of God) my life and converſation ſhall be a reall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of my traducers, and proclaime them liers. What I have now written in this Treatiſe, doth cleerely prove, that the Church of England is a true Church of Chriſt; that it is a ſin to ſeperate from it: that the Independent ſociety is no Church, and that it is a ſin to joyne to it. In all which my eye was upon God to pleaſe him, not upon men to pleaſe them; nay, I am perſwaded ſome godly men will be offended with me, who many times, through their miſtakes, looking upon grace and acts of grace as groſſe ſinnes, they cenſure men for exerciſing of their grace. Truth is, I had rather a milſtone were put about my neck,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.6.</note> and I caſt into the bottome of the ſea, then that I ſhould give them juſt cauſe of being offended; but if I become their enemy for telling them the truth,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.16.</note> I paſſe it not. Gods glory in the convincing of ſome that are in a way of error, and deterring of others from entring into ſuch a way, is the maine thing aimed at, which if obtained, let God have the glory, and your prayers be for him who remaines</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your friend in and for the truth, <hi>S.T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159848:4"/>
            <head>TRUTH VINDICATED From the falſe Accuſations of thoſe of the Independent Society, &amp;c.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Church of England is a true Church of Chriſt, for the cleering of this I will ſhew: Firſt, the divers acceptations of the word Church. 2. In what ſence the Church of England is ſaid to bee a true Church of Chriſt. 3. I will lay downe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments grounded upon the word of God, whereby it doth appeare, that the Church of England is a true Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the word Church is put, firſt, for all thoſe that ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. To the generall aſſembly and Church of the firſt born that are written in heaven, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.18 And he is the head of the body the Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is put for the faithfull of a family: we reade of the Church in Priſcillaes and Aquilaes houſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159848:4"/>of the Church in Nymphas houſe, Coloſ 4.15. And of the Church in Philemons houſe, Philemon verſe 2.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is put for the houſes or places where the faithfull do meete together to preach the word of God, and to adminiſter the Sacraments, as appeares if you compare, 1 Cor. 11.18 verſe with the 20 verſe. In the 18 verſe he ſaith, when ye come together in the Church: and in the 20. verſe when ye come together in one place.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is put for the profeſſors of Chriſt, ſcattered, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeverall Regions. Acts 8.13. Acts. 12.1. The Apoſtle Peter writing to the ſtrangers ſcattered throughout Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia, and Bithynia, in the 1 Peter 1.1. he calleth them in the ſecond Chapter of that Epiſtle, and the 5 verſe, lively ſtones, built up to a ſpirituall houſe; (that is a Church of God.)</p>
            <p>Fiftly, it is put for every congregation gathered together to worſhip God. 1 Cor. 14.23. If therefore the whole Church be come together into ſome place. 1 Cor. 4.17. As I teach every where in every Church.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, it is put for the repreſentative Church, that is thoſe who have the government of the Church in their hands, and are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the order, peace, and diſcipline of it: Mat. 18.17. And if he ſhall neglect to hear them, tell it to the Church; (that is to the Miniſters or Governors of the Church, who have power to caſt him out as a heathen man, and a publican:) not every particular member of the Church: as appeares by the Apoſtle 2 Cor. 2.6. ſufficient to ſuch a man, is this puniſhment (or cenſure) which was inflicted by many, he would not have reſtrained it to many if it had been done by all.</p>
            <p>Seventhly and laſtly, by Church in Scripture is underſtood a Kingdome or Nation, Province, County or City, enjoying the word, and ordinances of God, and profeſſing faith in God. Such a Church was the Church of the Jewes, to whom were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159848:5"/>the Oracles of God, Rom. 3.2. And from whom ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the word by which God worketh ſalvation, Iſay 2.3. By which word they were diſtinguiſhed from all other Nations in the World, Pſal. 147.19.20. and became the peculier people of God, Deut. 7.6. And thus the Kingdome of Iſrael, became the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, or Church of God. Our Saviour Chriſt ſpeaking of the rejection of the Iewes from being his people, and Church, over whom he raigned by his Word and Spirit, ſaith, Mat. 21.43. the Kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bringing forth the fruits thereof; intimating, that whatſoever Nation received, and believed the word of God, did become the Church, and people of God, as the Nation of the Jewes was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were rejected. The Prophet Iſay propheſying of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Gentiles, ſaith, Iſay 55.5. behold thou ſhall call a Nation thou kneweſt not, and Nations that knew not thee, ſhall run unto thee: by which it appeareth that whole Nations ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Church and people of God; according to that promiſe, Iſay 52.15. he ſhall ſprinkle many Nations. And thus ye have the divers acceptations of the word Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I come now in the ſecond place, to ſhew in what ſenſe the Church of England is ſaid to be a true Church of God: And that is according to the laſt acceptation of the word Church; which is when a Nation joyne themſelves to the Lord, by receiving pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, believing, and practiſing the word of God to ſalvation, by which God becomes their God, dwelling in the midſt of them, and they become his people, Pſal. 33.12. according to that in Zach. 2.11. and many Nations ſhall be joyned to the Lord in that day, and ſhall be my people, and I will dwell in the midſt of them: which was practiſed, Jerem. 50.5 Come let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall. Covenant, that ſhall not be forgotten. And it was moſt exactly performed in this Nation,<note place="margin">Deut. 26.17.18.</note> by our late Nationall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made with God. We read of a Covenant between God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159848:5"/>and his people, conſiſting of mutuall conditions; on the peoples part, the conditions are faith, whereby they embrace him, and rely upon him as their God; and obedience to his commands as their Lawmaker and Governour, verſe 17. and on Gods part, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are to take them for his people, which imployeth both his protection of them, and proviſion for them, both for this life, and the next: in this 18 verſe the Lord hath avouched thee this day to be his people: and in the 9 verſe of the next Chapter; this day thou art become the people of the Lord. Not, that they were not Gods Church and people before, for we find it expreſſed they were ſo: Deut, 7.6.7. Deut. 14.2. But hereby it is yet further confirmed to them, they were Gods Church and people. And thus, and in this ſence, the Church of England is a true Church of God: And this leads me to</p>
            <p>The third thing propounded, to lay downe arguments grounded upon the word of God, by which it cleerly appeares that the Church of England is a true Church of God. Our Saviour Chriſt, when he would prove to the woman of Samaria, that the Church of the Jewes, was the true Church of God, he doth it thus, Iohn 4.22. Ye worſhip ye know not what, we know what we worſhip, for ſalvation is of the Jewes. Whence I infer this firſt argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Church in which ſalvation is obtained, and God is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped according to the knowledge of his will revealed in his word, is the true Church of God; but in the Church of England, ſalvation is obtained, and God is worſhipped, according to his will revealed in his word: Therefore the Church of England is the true Church of God. A ſecond argument may be made which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily implied in the text; thus</p>
            <p n="2">2. Salvation is not ordinarily obtained out of the true Church of God; but ſalvation is ordinarily obtained (by the preaching of the word) in the Church of England: therfore the Church of England is the true Church of God. An other argument may be grounded
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159848:6"/>upon that by which the Apoſtle proves the Epheſians to be the true Church or houſhold of God, Ephe. 2.19.20.21. now therefore yee are no more ſtrangers and foraigners, but fellow Citizens with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God, and are built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles, and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe being the corner ſtone &amp;c. whence I frame this argument.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They that build upon the Apoſtles and Prophets making Chriſt the corner ſtone, are no ſtrangers but fellow Citizens with the Saints, and of the (Church or) houſhold of God; but the Church of England is ſound in Doctrine, building upon the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, making Chriſt Jeſus the corner ſtone: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the true Church of God.</p>
            <p>A fourth argument may be gathered, from that text: 1 Tim. 3.15. But if I tary long, that thou maiſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelfe in the houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God, the piller and ground of truth, by which text it appears, that truth is the ſigne whereby the Church of God is knowne: and from whence I thus reaſon.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Every Church that (as on a piller) hold forth the truth of God, is the houſe of God, the Church of the living God: But the Church of England, doe hold forth, the word of truth, Iohn 17.17. which is the Goſpel of Chriſt that bringeth ſalvation. Rom. 1.16. Therefore the Church of England is the true Church of God. I take theſe arguments for granted, and therefore I doe not prove all theſe things to be found in the Church of England; becauſe they are ſo cleerly manifeſt, that I thinke none will deny them; but if any ſhould, I deſire to know it, and I doubt not, but to ſatisfie them therein. There is one objection made by them that deny the Church of England to be a true Church; which I deſire to anſwer: It is this; the true Church of Chriſt, conſiſt of none but viſible Saints; but the Church of England is a mixt company of ignorant, wicked, and prophane perſons; Therefore they are not the true Church of God.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:159848:6"/>
            <p> To which I anſwer, That the true Church of Chriſt ought to conſiſt of none but viſible Saints for the well being thereof, is a truth; But that a Church ceaſes to be a true Church, becauſe they are not all viſible Saints, but ſome are ignorant wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons, this is falſe. The Church of Corinth was a true Church, yet ſome of them were ignorant, and had not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34. ſome denyed the Reſurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.12. ſome were wicked and prophane, for they were drunke when they came to the Sacrament, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. Therefore not all viſible Saints, yet a true Church. In the Church of Galatia ſome erred in the great point of juſtification, againſt which errour Saint Paul oppoſed his Epiſtle written to them, and yet they were a true Church. In the Church in Pergamos, ſome held the doctrine of Balam and of the Nicholaitans, teaching to eate things ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14. ſurely therefore not all viſible Saints, and yet a true Church of God. In the Church there are veſſels of wood and earth, as well as of gold and ſilver, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. And thus it appeares, that notwithſtanding there are ignorant, wicked and prophane perſons in the Church of England, yet it is the true Church of God. And ſo I come to the ſecond propoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That it is a ſin to ſeperate from the true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ought not to depart from a Church in which God dwels and abides, leſt we be found departers from God: But God wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the midſt of his Church, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.1. yea, he deſireth to dwell there, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.13, 14. and he promiſeth to walke amongſt them, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.12. therefore it cannot but be a ſin to ſeperate and walke from them. Our Saviour Chriſt did not ſeperate from the Church of the Jews, (although it was exceedingly corrupted, in worſhip, doctrine and diſcipline, they ſaying well but doing, ill yet)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159848:7"/>he was circumciſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.21. and baptiſed in it, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.21. hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding communion with it. In the Apologeticall Narration, <hi>pag.</hi> 6. they profeſſe before God and all the world, that multitudes of the Aſſemblies and parochiall Congregations of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land are the true Church and body of Chriſt, and the Miniſtery thereof a true Miniſtery: And when the Churches of England were the moſt either actually overſpread with deſilements, or in the greateſt danger thereof, they then both did, and would hold a communion with them, as the Churches of Chriſt. If this was their judgement then, certainely, now that wee are cleanſed from thoſe defilements, and a further Reformation is dayly intended and endeavoured; they cannot but acknowledge it to be a great ſin to ſeperate from our parochiall Churches, renouncing them as falſe Churches, and utterly denying to hold communion with them. I ſhall not need further to cleere this: All acknowledge it to be a ſin to ſeperate from the true Church; They in the Apologe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Narration do acknowledge our parochiall Churches, to bee the true Churches, and body of Chriſt. Therefore I proceed to the third thing propounded.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the Independent Society (in the City of Norwich) is no true Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall do it by theſe following arguments: the firſt is this, They that ſeperate from the true Church of Chriſt, are Schiſmaticks; And a company of Schiſmaticks, being joyned in ſociety together, make a ſociety of Schiſmaticks, but not a true Church of Chriſt: But the Independent Society, doe ſeperate from the Church of England, which (as hath beene proved) is the true Church of Chriſt: Therefore the Independent Society is no true Church of Chriſt. The Major propoſition is cleered to mee by that text in 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.19. where it appeares, that they that ſeperate from the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159848:7"/>Church, cannot be members of the Church. Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> in his fourth book of Conſcience, <hi>pag.</hi> 141. In his anſwer to this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether or no Schiſmaticks are members of the true Church? ſaith, If an obſtinate ſeperation be made from all true Churches, or from any one for, a caſe common to all, then ſuch Schiſmaticks (although it may be retaining the faith, they continue members of the Church Catholike) they cannot be eſteemed as viſible members of the Church. And for the Minor propoſition, themſelves cannot deny but they were converted in the Church of England: And it is a ſtrange Paradox to me, that they ſhould be converted in a falſe Church, and ſo made fit members for a true Church. Certainely, that Church in which they had their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fathers to beget them to God, that Church is their ſpirituall Mother. The Apoſtle ſaith, the Church of Corinth, had ten thouſand inſtructors in Chriſt, yet not many fathers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.15. but (bleſſed be God) in the Church of England, there are, and have beene many ſpirituall fathers, who through the preaching of the Goſpel of Chriſt, have and doe daily beget many to Chriſt; and they are the Miniſters of God by whom wee beleeve, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. And yet theſe Miniſters are ſlighted (if not deſpiſed) and counted no Miniſters of God: And the Church in which they were converted and brought home to God, is rejected and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no Church of God: and can ſuch a Society be the true Church of Chriſt? ſurely no.</p>
            <p>A ſecond and third argument to prove them to be no Church, I gather from their owne tenents: In deſcribing of a true Church, they did affirme (at a meeting for diſpute) that it was abſolutely neceſſary for the being of a Church, that there ſhould be forme as well as matter, and they ſaid forme was a Church Covenant, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which a Church did ceaſe to be a true Church: But I my ſelfe have ſeene members received into their Society without a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: (which one of the chiefe of them told me, was to ſhew they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159848:8"/>did not abſolutely require it) Therefore according to their owne rule, they did then ceaſe to be a true Church.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſome of them have affirmed that the forme of a Church is government or Church diſcipline (which I take to be the forme of a true Church rather then the other) but if ſo, then their Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot be a true Church, For they have never a Church Officer, therefore cannot execute Church diſcipline: It is the Elders of the Church, that are to rule the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. But that Society have never an Elder, nor other Church Officers; therefore they want forme or government; and therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their owne argument they are no Church.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, how can that be a true Church, that take in members when in their eſteeme they are good, when they have no power to caſt them out, though they ſhould prove never ſo bad? certainely, in ſuch a Church as this, all things cannot be done decently and in order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. but for want of power to puniſh the diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nothing but confuſion will (in time) bee found in ſuch a Church: And certainly, God is not the Author of ſuch a Church, in which there is nothing but confuſion, and no meanes to prevent it. Gods Church is his building, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. his houſe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. Fiftly framed, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.21. and formed by himſelfe for himſelfe, <hi>Eſay</hi> 43.21. hee having appointed in it Stewards, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. and all other Officers for the well ordering of it. But a Society gathered together, without Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers over them, to ſee peace and order continued amongſt them, will in a ſhort time be a Babell for confuſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.9. but cannot be the true Church of Chriſt: For, God is not the Author of confuſion, but of peace, as in all the Churches of the Saints, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. And thus you ſee that the Independent Society in the City of Norwich, is no Church. I come now to the fourth and laſt thing propounded.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:159848:8"/> 4. <hi>To lay downe divers reaſons and arguments to perſwade men not uſeperate from the Church of England, and joyne to the Independent ſociety ſhewing the unlawfullneſſe of ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it is a direct violation of our oath made with our hands lift up to the moſt high God, in our ſolemne League and Covenant. In the firſt Article thereof, we covenanted to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the neereſt conjunction, and vniformity in Religion, confeſſion of faith, forme of Church government, directory for worſhip and catechizing: And in the ſecond Article, we covenanted to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the extirpation of Schiſme &amp;c. leſt we be partakers in other mens ſins; but how doe thoſe take this Covenant, with a true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to performe it, (as is expreſſed in the latter part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,) who deny the Churches of the three Kingdoms to be true Churches, and ſet up a new Church (as they call it) againſt, and contrary to the government eſtabliſhed, (or about to be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed) in the Churches of the three Kingdoms? Is this to endeavour the uniformity of Church government, and the extirpation of Schiſme, that the Lord may be one, and his name one in the three Kingdoms? Or is it not a retarding of the worke of Reformation, and the ſetling of Church government? And the ſpreading of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, ſchiſmes, factions, and diviſions amongſt us. We are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to keepe our vowes. (Deut. 23.21. Ecle. 5.4. And Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant breakers are reckoned amongſt thoſe that are given up to a reprobate minde. (Rom. 1.13.) And God hath threatned the ſword, to avenge the quarrell of his Covenant, Levit. 26.25. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a greivous ſin to breake Covenant: And whether or no the Independents, keepe, or breake their Covenant, let the world judge.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, to joyne in fellowſhip with the Independent ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159848:9"/>doth hinder men from walking with God in ſuch a way wherein they may moſt honour him, in the uſe of all his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; in performing of all thoſe mutuall duties, that God requires of his children one towards another. For firſt they deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the cheife miniſteriall Ordinances of God, as the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word of God, and the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: For as they looke upon the Church of England, as no Church, ſo alſo upon our Miniſters, as no Miniſters: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they prefer their owne private meetings, before our publique preaching: And amongſt themſelves they have no Church Officer to performe any of theſe miniſteriall acts: And therefore they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not honour God in the uſe of thoſe Ordinances, as they might have done, if they had continued in that Church of God, in which they did injoy them. Secondly, they cannot honour God in the performing of all thoſe mutuall duties, that God requires of his children one towards another; for ſeperating from the Church of England as a falſe Church, they looke upon all the members of it, as without the pale of the Church, (and they cannot otherwiſe doe while they are of that judgement.) And becauſe they are ſo, they thus reaſon, as for thoſe with whom we have entred into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and are members of our Church, we are bound to, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they are without, and what have we to doe with thoſe that are without, ſay they? Whereas we know it is Chriſts command that all the faithfull ſhould love one another, Iohn 13.34. and they ought alſo to have fellowſhip one with another, 1 Iohn 13. and by love to ſerve one another, Gal. 5.13. and to let brotherly love continue, Heb. 13.1. conſtantly provoking one another to love and to good workes, Heb 10.24. exhorting and inſtructing the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Heb. 3.13. Dan. 11.33. incouraging and ſtrengthning the weake, 1 Theſ. 5.14. Iob 4.3.4. but all theſe duties are neglected, by them that ſeperate, and walke at a diſtance from other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whereby they rob them of that ſpirituall good, that charity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159848:9"/>requires (and formerly they have done to others;) and deprive themſelves alſo, of that edification, they might receive (and have formerly received) by their communion with them: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a ſin to joyne with ſuch a ſociety, as thus hinder men from performing of their dutie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, by ſeperating from the Church of England and joyning to the Independent ſociety: Divine precepts are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated: For we are commanded that all thingss ſhould be done in charity, 1 Cor. 16.14. &amp; it is a ſin not to walke charitably, Rom. 14.15. but what charity is it to renounce a whole Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ground? It is true Gods people are commanded to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from Heathens and Idolaters, 2 Cor. 6.17. Iſa. 52.11. to depart out of Babilon, Revel. 18.4. but not out of Sion: Not forſaking the aſſemblings of Gods Church and people. Heb. 10.25. Therefore they that ſeperate muſt account the Church of England as Babylon, they muſt reckon them amongſt the Heathens and Idolaters, or elſe they cannot juſtifie their ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from them. And if they ſo Judge, where is their charity? Againe ſaith the Apoſtle, Rom. 16.17. now I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren marke them which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned and avoyd them: And we are commanded not to meddle (or mix our ſelves) with thoſe that are given to change, Prov. 24.21. And well may ſuch receive that checke, that the Prophet Jeremie giveth, Jer. 2.36. why gaddeſt thou about ſo much to change thy way: But how doe thoſe performe theſe precepts that cauſe diviſions and ſeperations, and gad about ſo much to change their way?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is denounced as a judgement of God to be ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the Congregation of Gods Church and people. Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra 10.8. But the Independent ſocietie make themſelves the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners of this judgement upon themſelves; for God caſts
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159848:10"/>them not out, neither doth the Church caſt them out, but themſelves ſeperate themſelves from the Church and people of God: &amp; what greater evill, then under pretence of joyning to the Church of God, to depart from the Church, in the midſt whereof God abides, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 46.5. Is it not to depart from God?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, by ſeperating from the true Church of God, the unity of Chriſts myſticall body is (in a manner) deſtroyed: for all the faithfull are of one houſhold, <hi>Gal</hi> 6.10. children of one and the ſame father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.6. and mother, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26. hauing all one elder brother, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. and are all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by the ſame ſpirituall ſeed, 1 <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.23. and are all nouriſhed by the ſame milke, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.2. and are all heires of the ſame kingdome, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. all ſouldiers under the ſame Captaine, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. all having the ſame enemies, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. Therefore it cannot but be a great ſin for them to ſeperate and divide.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, they that ſeperate cauſe diviſions, and diſcover them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bee carnall in ſo doing, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. for ye are yet carnall, for whereas there is amongſt you envying and ſtrife, and diviſions, (or factions) are yee not carnall, and walke as men? (as carnall and wicked men) <hi>Iude</hi> ver. 19. Theſe be they that ſeperate themſelves, ſenſuall, having not the Spirit, (or as ſome reade the words, Theſe are makers of Sects) &amp;c.) and in the verſe before, they are called mockers. Wee finde that haters of Gods people ſeperated Gods people from their company, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.22. but wee finde not Gods people reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of, and ſeperating themſelves from the company of the Church and people of God: yet ſo do the Independents.</p>
            <p>Seventhly and laſtly, they that ſeperate from the Church of England, to joyne to the Independent Society; they are meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceived of their ends in their joyning; for firſt, they thinke
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159848:10"/>they joyne themſelves to a true Church, but they doe not. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they thinke they ſhall be bettered by their joyning with them, but they are not. Firſt, in their joyning with them, they are ſo farre from joyning to a true Church, as thereby they caſt themſelves out of a true Church, and are made members of no Church: And (if I miſtake not) they that excommunicate a whole Church of God, and themſelves out of it, by renouncing it, are in a worſe condition then thoſe that are excommunicated and caſt out by the Church; for caſting out by the Church is for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may bee ſaved, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. And although the Church account of ſuch a one as a Heathen and a Publican, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. yet he that is ſo rejected, doth not reject the Church, and count them as Heathens and Publicans: But they that thus reject the Church of England, do account of them as Heathens and Publicans, that is to ſay, ſuch a company as it is not fit to hold communion with as the Church of God. Now let who will judge, who is in the worſt condition, either he that is rejected by the Church as a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt ſinne, or he that is not rejected by the Church, yet make it his ſin to deſpiſe and reject the whole Church? And how a company of ſuch deſpiſers and rejecters of the Church of God, ſhould make a Church of God, I know not. Secondly, they that joyne themſelves to that moſt ſtrange Independent Society, are exceedingly deceived, in thinking they ſhall be bettered by ſo doing. I know the benefit, by mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for prayer and conference, is that which is much aymed at by ſome that are joyned with them, and others that have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee joyned with them (for that end) but are not. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the meetings of chriſtians, for prayer and conference, are duties I much priſe and approve of, and have found much bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by them, but it was when there was more ſincerity, humility,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159848:11"/>and familiarity amongſt chriſtians, then is generally now to bee found: Of late it is come to paſſe (through the pollicy of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and the pride and deceitfulneſſe of mens hearts) that under pretence of meeting for the performing of theſe duties, mens fancies are vented, and all the errours amongſt us, are dayly ſpread and increaſed; and how can it otherwiſe be, when theſe duties are performed by thoſe whoſe judgements are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted? When chriſtian ſociety was maintained in humility and the feare of God, with all that feared God, then God did approve of their meeting, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. and they found the fruit of it: But ſince pride and ſingularity have made a ſeperation, (ſo as not all that feare God are admitted into their Society, but onely ſuch as are of their judgement, and will walke with them in their way) God hath not approved of their Society; for God is no (ſuch) reſpecter of perſons, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34.35. neither would he have chriſtian conference hindered for any ſuch ends. Gal. 2.6. And while it is ſo hindered, how can God be glorified, or themſelves bettered thereby? Doth not experience prove, they are the worſe, ſince they have entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Independent ſociety? Doe they not neglect publique or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? Are not (many of them) remiſſe in family duties? Are not Gods Miniſters neglected (if not deſpiſed?) Are not former Freinds ſlighted and rejected? At leaſt, is not their love to them abated? Doe they not miſconſtrue every mans words and actions, that are not in their affections? who have been more ready then they to receive and ſpread abrode (if not to raiſe) falſe reports of others, that have not complied with them? Have any credited and divulged, the ſcandalous reports that have been raiſed of our Brethren the Scots, more then they? Doe not their very ſpeech bewray, that they would be glad, if there were ſufficient matter of charge againſt them, to occaſion falling
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159848:11"/>with violence upon them? Have they not high thoughts of themſelves? Doe each of them in lowlineſſe of mind eſteeme others better then themſelves? Phil. 2.3. Doe they abate in ſin, and increaſe in grace? But can ſin abate where love decaies, Mat. 24.12. or grace grow, where pride increaſes? James. 4.6. Surely no. Can a man ſin againſt God and proſper? Job 9.4. It is true they that love the Church ſhall proſper, Pſal. 122, 6. but can any caſt off the Church and proſper? While a man is in a way of ſinning againſt God, I cannot but queſtion his thriving in grace. I confeſſe I have heard much boaſting of their thriving in the Independent ſociety, but I have not ſeene it. I find not growing Thyatira boaſting of their growth, Rev. 2.18.19. but I find decaying Laodicea, vaine gloriouſly boaſting of their riches and increaſe, but it was their ignorance made them thinke ſo, for they were wretched, miſerable, poore, blind and naked, notwithſtanding their boaſting, Rev. 3.14.17. To conclude, if to joyne with the Independent ſociety, be a viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant: a hindering men from performing their duties to others: a violating of divine precepts: a bringing a judgement of God upon themſelves: a breaking the unity of Chriſts myſticall body: a diſcovering themſelves to be carnall, a ſeperating themſelves from the true Church, and making themſelves to be no members of any Church of God: and a meere deluding themſelves: All which hath been proved it is: Therefore it cannot but be a ſin, and folly to joyne to that ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. Conſider what hath been ſaid, and the Lord give you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
